<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter written by a French gentleman to a friend of his at Rome conteyning a true report of the late treaty betweene the Queene Mother of France and King of Nauarre / faithfully translated out of French.</title>
            <author>Thārư̄a Phānit Sattahīp (Thailand)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1587</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08789</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19078.6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2262</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23203131</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23203131</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26389</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08789)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26389)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1801:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter written by a French gentleman to a friend of his at Rome conteyning a true report of the late treaty betweene the Queene Mother of France and King of Nauarre / faithfully translated out of French.</title>
                  <author>Thārư̄a Phānit Sattahīp (Thailand)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>T. Orwin? for E. Aggas],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1587.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: S.C.P.</note>
                  <note>Publisher statement suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catherine de Médicis, --  Queen, consort of Henry II, King of France, 1519-1589.</term>
               <term>Henry --  IV, --  King of France, 1553-1610.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26389:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26389:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER written by a French <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman to a friend of his at Rome:</hi> Conteyning A true report of the late treaty betweene the Queene Mother of <hi>France</hi> and the King of <hi>Nauarre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully translated out of French.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted:</hi> 1587.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:26389:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26389:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Letter written by a <hi>French Gentleman vnto a friend of</hi> his at <hi>Rome,</hi> conteyning a true diſcourſe <hi>of the late voyage made by the Queene the Kings Mother into</hi> Poictow.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV haue ſondrie tymes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted mee to impart vnto you that hope which I had conceyued of the Queene Mother our Miſteriſſes late iourney. All your letters doe obiect vnto me too much breuitie in this argument: Now therefore muſt I ſatiſfie you, which I would ſooner haue done if I could haue ſatiſfied my ſelf: But to tell you the truth, I alwaies had ſmall hope of this treatie. I doubted to ſend you my aduice leaſt you ſhould haue diſlyked it, neither could I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe of yours in reſpect of ſondrie great reaſons which I gathered therein, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering they haue holden out againſt your authoritie. Beleue me my Lord, in a place
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26389:3"/> of quiet you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not iudge of our diſquiet: At Rome it is not poſsible for you well to conſider of ſuch controuerſies as are in France: you would be of another opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if in liewe of tryumphant Porches you ſhould make your walkes through a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted Countrey: In ſtead of poliſhed Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you ſhould vnder your feete ſee the bodies of your friends and fellowe Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens: and in place of fayre Fountaynes the ſtreames of blud ſhould runne round about you. If with your owne eyes you ſhould behold our miſchiefes they would ſeeme greater vnto you then eyther the paper can conteyne or your eares admit, which finding to bee ſo, you would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the remedie to bee the more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult.</p>
            <p>I remember when the Queene began her voyadge you thought nothing vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that ſhe tooke in hand, and did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt the peace fully concluded if ſhee were but willing to ſpeake of it: and for my owne parte, my ſelfe did beleeue that if ſhee fayled, it was not for any other to take it in hand. I was euer of that opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26389:3"/> that her perſon was cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ningly choſen, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe in that commoditie I founde diuers diſcommodities, &amp; in that which ſeemed moſt perfect ſondrie defaults: I was not ignorant that the <hi>Guyzes</hi> ſhe had made greatly beholding vnto her, and ſo conſequently might do much with them: but withall ſhe had highly prouoked the houſe of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> who might iuſtly bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den her with their laſt warre, aſwell as the others held the laſt peace of her. I percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that ſhee choſe ſuch Counſailors as were meete to ſuppreſſe whatſoeuer ielo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie the League might conceiue in her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: but withall fit to cauſe thoſe of the Religion to repoſe no confidence in her: Neither was this al: for as I thought ſome of them very vnfit for this treatie, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe was the time in my opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wel worſe choſen. At one inſtant I ſaw the Queenes prouiſion made readie, and at the ſame tyme three or fower Armies leuyed: I thought it a hard matter to bring thoſe whome they made reſolute to the warre, of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be well diſpoſed to peace: and in deede the Queene ſomewhat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26389:4"/> my expectation, for ſhe departed ſoner than I could ſee any reaſon for her ſo to doe. Now ſhall you haue the whole diſcourſe of our voyadge, the perticulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties whereof I haue diligently noted, as wel to ſatiſfie your curioſitie, as alſo to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer your opinion conceiued of my dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence: and I would to God wee could as eaſely refourme ſuch ouerſights as our great Counſailors haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, as your ſelfe can readily eſpye them out.</p>
            <p>You knowe that at one and the ſame tyme ſhe gaue notice to the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre</hi> of her ſetting forwarde, and to the Lords of <hi>Montpenſier</hi> and <hi>Montmorency</hi> of her purpoſe, requeſting them both to worke the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> to the peace. This firſt action did diuers men diuerſly conſter: ſome ſayd that too euidently ſhe confeſſed to the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> that ſhe had offended him, in that ſhe (beeing his Mother) did procure ſollicitours to moue him. Thoſe of the League feared this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and thoſe of the Religion had it in ſuſpect. Some doubted the Duke of <hi>Montpenſiers</hi> authoritie, others his faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26389:4"/> Thoſe of the League ſayde that the Queene ſet him at one with the chiefe of his famelie: Thoſe of the Religion, that the Queenes counſayle tended to make him a ſolliciter of peace to the King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> thereby to turne him from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his companyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the warre. Thus you ſee both parts grow into miſtruſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue the one to defend, &amp; the other the more fiercely to offend: and in deede ſo faſt as the Queene haſted forwarde, the Duke of <hi>Maine</hi> haſted to come to <hi>Paris,</hi> and ſo ſone as the treaty of peace began, the purpoſes of the League proceeded. The Abbot of <hi>Gadaigne</hi> beeing the firſt tyme ſent to the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well enterteyned, whervpon euery one aſſured himſelfe of the wiſhed benefite: but this hope vaniſhed like a flaſh of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: for euen at his ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d voyage which he made while the Queene was at <hi>Cheno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eau</hi> wee ſmelt out that bitterneſſe which the courteſies &amp; firſt offers of ſeruice had before cloked and ſweetened. <hi>Gadaignes</hi> paſſage by <hi>Brouage</hi> the <hi>Rochellers</hi> did ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, and the reuictualing of <hi>Brouage</hi> did
<pb facs="tcp:26389:5"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:26389:5"/>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:26389:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:26389:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:26389:7"/> they accompt to bee a ſtorehouſe againſt their Towne. Neuertheleſſe, the Queene Mother came forwarde to haſten the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruiewe: The King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> would come with ſafetie &amp; credite. The Queene willed him wholly to repoſe himſelf vpon her: The King would that ſhe ſhould truſt him. She alleadged her goodwill: and he made accompt of his fidelitie and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie. She obiected to him that he was the onely hinderer of the enteruiewe: he replyed that ſhee was the onely let, that <hi>France</hi> was not at quiet: alſo that he was readie to ſee her, ſo that it might bee in a ſafe place and the way free. And for the place, he offered to come to <hi>Champigny,</hi> in caſe the Marſhall of <hi>Birons</hi> troupes might depart and goe ouer the Riuer of <hi>Loyre:</hi> this he ſeemed to requeſt as well for his owne ſafetie, as alſo to put in hope his partakers, of whom ſome perſwaded him to ſuccour <hi>Castillon:</hi> others not to truſt to words, but rather hereafter to looke for like enterteynment as he had had before tyme. I muſt not lye. The King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> for his part, ſhewed himſelf greatly affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26389:7"/> to the weale &amp; benefit of this Realm, and in caſe the Queene deceiued mee in going to him, he did farther fayle my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation in tarying for her. But ſee: euen as they were determining vpon the place and maner of the enteruiew there appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red an Army vpon the Sea before <hi>Rochelb.</hi> Conſider I pray you whether thoſe that miſliked and withſtood this meeting, had a large argument to declayme vppon: All was at the poynt to breake of. The King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> could not perſwade himſelfe that they which ſo purſued him both by Sea &amp; by land, had any deſire or meaning to do him good. The Queene was cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to wearie him with warres thereby to obteyne the better peace, and yet percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not that theſe counſaylors did vſe her fauour to the ende to driue the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> into diſpayre; who therevppon complayned to the King by the Lorde of <hi>Reaux,</hi> and beſought their Maieſties to call backe the ſayd Armie, declaring that hee could not leaue a Towne of ſo great importance as <hi>Rochell</hi> in that eſtate: and iudging without parcialitie, I find that he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26389:8"/> had reaſon: how beit the Nauy ſtirred not away ſo long as it had victuals, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding whatſoeuer the king of <hi>Nauarres</hi> petitions, but famine hoyſed the ſayles thereof, and not the Kings commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: For to the contrary, euen the ſame day that it wayed ancre, Captayne <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> was taken with the Queene Mothers letters to the Commander of <hi>Chatte,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning him not to depart, or at the leaſt not to goe farre away. Theſe letters fell into the King of <hi>Nauarres</hi> hands, yet he, neglecting whatſoeuer imaginations he might iuſtly conceyue, did neuertheleſſe offer to ſee the Queene vppon the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions aforeſayde, requiring that in the meane tyme al hoſtilitie might ceaſe: The Queene deſired the publicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a truce, whereto he ſayde he could not agree, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee had before bene driuen to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe his partakers that hee would not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree vppon any peace or truce without their aduice and conſent. This anſwer ſhe found very ſtrange and had a better taſte thereof then when it was foretold her by the Lords of <hi>Lenoncourt &amp; Poigny.</hi> Which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26389:8"/> putteth me in mynd of the <hi>Carthagenians,</hi> who wept and howled when they ſhould pay their tribute to the <hi>Romains,</hi> but were nothing moued when they became their tributaries. When the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> told theſe our Maiſters that he would yet ſixe moneths attende the Kings ſuccour before he would employ his friends, and that he would be denyed of peace before he would reſolue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> warre, they did but laugh at his pacience: but now that wee ſee he hath giuen his word, we weepe, and truely for no other cauſe but for that we wept not when we enfringed the Edicts, when we accompted the innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t guiltie, the obedient ſubiectes Rebelles, and iuſt men offenders. Well, after many difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and diuers iourneys too and fro the Queene ſent ſondry Paſſeports which the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> had demaunded to the end to aduertiſe his frends, and preſently therewith publiſhed a Truce, which was like to haue mard all againe: for the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> ſuſpected that they would take aduantage of the publication there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of againſt a leauie of Reyſters that he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:26389:9"/> made in <hi>Germany,</hi> and therefore declared to her Maieſtie that in as much as this act had relation to a common aſſurance, it ought alſo to haue bene concluded by a common conſent: wherevpon this publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation was made voyde. Afterward trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon the ſolemne reiterating of the ſame, certeine troupes of the regiment of <hi>Neufuy</hi> were aſſaulted, which wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully diſpleaſed the King of <hi>Nauarre.</hi> The want of diſcretion in our Capteynes made men to weene that we had great ſtomacks. In the end little <hi>Roche</hi> ſo trotted to and fro, that the enteruiewe was concluded and the truce publiſhed. The King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> came the eleuenth day of December to <hi>Iarnac,</hi> and the thirtenth of the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, being very well accompanyed, ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her Maieſtie at S. <hi>Bris.</hi> Here do I leaue to your imagination the manifolde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnts on eyther part.</p>
            <p>The Queene charged him with diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and ouerſlipping all former actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſtayed chiefly vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the preſent calamities<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhe gaue him to vnderſtand that the king, for ſauing his owne eſtate, was forced to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26389:9"/> make peace with the League: that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that ſhift all had bin loſt: that for the ceaſing of the warres in the Realme, hee muſt of neceſsitie habandon all pretence of Religion.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> complayned that all the domages that he had ſuſteyned, had growne to him onely for his obedience to their Maieſties: That the League was waxen ſtrong, onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee had remayned weake: That hee had put his life in hazard by keeping his faith: Further, reducing the preſent miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes to their firſt originall, he referred the miſerie of this Realme to the peace concluded with the League: he affirmed that the King had bene euill counſayled rather then compelled: That the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the eſtate depended vppon the mainteining of his Edicts: That ſuch were in deed his edicts as he had of his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord ſworn vnto: That the edicts of peace were thoſe which baniſhed warres, but not thoſe which for the contenting of a few ſedicious perſons, ſtart vp in one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, repleniſhed the whole Realm with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26389:10"/> vprores. Madame, ſayde hee, you cannot accuſe mee but of ouer much fidelitie: I blame not your faith, but your age, which doing iniurie to your memorie, cauſeth you ſone to forget your promiſe vnto me. This was the end of that meeting, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the very laſt wordes. Men began to hope for much courteſie at the next, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the bitter taunts ſeemed to bee wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed away in the former.</p>
            <p>The Vicount of <hi>Touraine</hi> came to <hi>Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nac</hi> to conclude vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome perticularities concerning the truce, where the Queene gaue him to vnderſtand that for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect obteyning of a peace the king of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre</hi> muſt needes become a Catholicke, and put downe all exerciſe of any other Religion throughout all thoſe Townes which were in his poſſeſsion: ſhe farther gaue him perticuler charge to certefie the ſayde King that ſuch was the Kings plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and hers. As I heard, whiles the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> was on his way to come and ſee the Queene, the Vicount of <hi>Touraine</hi> aforeſayd, met with him, and at large de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered him his charge: whervpon he was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26389:10"/> about to haue returned back againe. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, imagining with himſelfe that the Queene, for the feeding of her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes humours, had propounded thoſe ſpeeches, he determined to goe forward, aſwell for the ſatiſfying of his own mynd, as alſo to the end to giue her Maieſtie an anſwer: howbeit euen as ſoone as he with a ſad and heauie countenance had kiſſed her Maieſties hands, ſhe aſked him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Vicount of <hi>Touraine</hi> had yet ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with him, aſſuring him that that meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage was the Kings reſolute determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: whereto hee anſwered her, that hee greatly marueiled her Maieſtie woulde take vpon her ſo great a trauayle, only to tell him of a matter, with the hearing whereof his eares were alreadie euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nummed: That he wondered that ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo great iudgement would thus linger in ſeeking to diſſolue a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie by the very difficultie it ſelfe: That ſhe now propounded vnto him a matter which he could by no meanes performe without offence to both his Conſcience &amp; honor, yea ſuch a one as ſhe could not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:26389:11"/> requeſt without doing greate iniurie to the Kings ſeruice. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the offence againſt his owne Conſcience only GOD and his Conſcience were the iudges ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and for his honor he beſought her to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider what iniurie he ſhould offer ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, if he ſhould in any reſpect yeeld more to his enemies weapons, then vnto his Kings commaundements: That in caſe he ſhould ſo farre ouerſhoot and forget him ſelfe, yet lay it not in him thereby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poke all the reſt that profeſſed the ſame Religion: That thereby the pretence of the houſe of <hi>Guyze</hi> ſhoulde augment ſo much the more, by how much their hope ſhould fayle them of being any way able to debarre him of all ſuch right as vnto him may appertayne: That in the augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their pretence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſted the force of their weapons, &amp; in the force of their weapons the deſtruction of this eſtate: This only Madame, ſayd he, ſhould I doe to my owne contentation. viz. Beeing a Catholicke and winning to my ſelfe the fauour &amp; goodwill of my Lord the King, I might, in approching nerer about him.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:26389:11"/> enioye the honour and benefite to yeeld vnto him my bounden ſeruice: but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all I ſhould doe more for my enemies, in this, that remayning alone I might mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vnto them ſit oportunitie to take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you the moſt faithfulleſt ſeruant that euer you ſhall haue: neyther will they ſuffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch about you, fearing leaſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues might ſo growe miſerable and wretched, you better ſerued, and all your good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects more happie. Hereto the Queene made no anſwer, (for in deede it had bin a harde matter to make any good) but ſtood vpon the laying before him al ſuch diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities as by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance of warre he did ſuſteyne: I doe, ſayd he, moſt pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently beare them, becauſe that you, to the end to diſburthen your ſelf, haue wholly layd them vppon me. In this diſcourſe ſhe proceeded ſo farre that at length ſhe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected vnto him that in <hi>Rochell</hi> hee could not doe whatſoeuer he liſted: Pardon me Madame, ſayd hee, for I will or liſt to doe nothing but what I ought. Then the Lord of <hi>Neuers</hi> interrupting her, told him that it lay not in him there to leauy an impoſt:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26389:12"/> True, ſayd he, neither haue we any <hi>Italians</hi> among vs. Soone after the Queene mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned for a general truce to be taken for one whole yere, vpon condition that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſame all exerciſe of the Religion might ceaſe throughout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole Realm, &amp; in the meane tyme the generall eſtates to be holden: To this he anſwered that in caſe thoſe of the Religion ſhould ſo eaſely habandon and giue ouer their holds and places of retreate, the league would ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by grow the ſtronger, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the eſtates the weaker: That he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it vnpoſsible to ſurceaſe &amp; extinguiſh the exerciſe of the Religion in <hi>France</hi> by any other meanes then by a good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: alſo that the King remayning as yet the weaker, hee accompted the aſſembly of the eſtates to be in vayne &amp; to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: That the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of the eſtates hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at <hi>Bloys</hi> did verefie the one, and the vayne endeuours of the Kings predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors the other. Then as he was taking his leaue of her, the Queene did many tymes repeat vnto him the ſame diſcourſe which as is aforeſayd ſhe had before holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:26389:12"/> the Vicount of <hi>Touraine,</hi> charging him to impart the ſame to the reſt of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that followed him, which eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the next morning he did, and that, as ſince I haue bene certefied, with very great griefe, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring leaſt it might worke ſome alteration in euery mans general deſire of peace: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that hee choſe the moſt peaceable mynded perſons in his troupe, namely, the Lords of <hi>Monguion</hi> and <hi>Force,</hi> as well to teſtifie to her Maieſtie that great griefe which euery man had conceiued in ſeing themſelues reduced to ſo extreme a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie through this her extreme reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as alſo to enquire whether there were no more to bee expected of that authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie which the King had vnto her giuen. The Queene herevpon ſeeing her ſelfe at the poynt eyther wholly to breake, or at the leaſt wiſe to morgage her promiſe, tolde them that ſhe would ſend the Lord of <hi>Rambouillet</hi> to deſire the kings Maieſtie of his finall determination, which (I wot not to what purpoſe) ſhe thought good to make vncerteyne, as it appeared aſwell by this, as alſo by her ſpeeches to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duke
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:26389:13"/> of <hi>Montpenfier,</hi> whom ſhe told that al that which ſhe had ſaid to the Vicount of <hi>Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine</hi> was by way of diſcourſe only, but ſhe ſhewed him not that in expreſſe termes ſhee had deliuered it to the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre,</hi> whom as ſhe ſayd ſhe was very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous againe to ſee, and therefore expreſly charged him to motion the prolonging of the truce, which he did, beeing on his way to bid him farewell.</p>
            <p>Among ſo many contrarieties no man wiſt what to ſay, or my ſelfe to write vnto you. Some ſuppoſed that to the ende to content and ſatiſfie the League ſhe would not open any meanes to peace, except in ſhewing her ſelfe to be thereto forced by neceſsitie. Others were of opinion that her Councell ſtill fed her with ſome newe hope conceiued and grounded vpon the weake eſtate of the affaires of thoſe of the Religion, and ſo promiſing her to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the obteyning of ſome ſuch peace as ſhould be greatly to the kings liking, they did vnder ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d leade her into ſuch a warre as might redound to the benefite of the League. After that the Lord of <hi>Rambouil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:26389:13"/> was returned &amp; had made his reporte, viz. That the King had ſworne by all the ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nities of the order of the holy Ghoſt, that he would neuer in any wiſe conſent to permit any exerciſe of the Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the Queene procured the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> to bee earneſtly mooued to an other enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiewe, cunningly cauſing him to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that he would very wel like of the Lord of <hi>Rambouillets</hi> returne, whereto ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe it was very hard to make him to condiſcend, in that his hope which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee had repoſed in the ſeeing of the Queene, was now, if not quite quayled &amp; loſt, yet at the leaſt very farre ſtrayed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye. His partakers earneſtly diſwaded him therefro, as miſtruſting that her only purpoſe tended to continue the parley that ſhe had before entered: himſelf dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the often renewing of the truce, and the rather for that he was giuen to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that the publication of the firſt was vndoubtedly put in print and tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both into <hi>Suitzerland</hi> and <hi>Germanie.</hi> Some ſayd that ſhee ſtill lingered him on with a treatie of peace, to the ende to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26389:14"/> fit opportunitie &amp; conuenient time to make warre vpon him: Others, that ſhe propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto him moſt greeuous and intollerable conditions, thereby to force him firſt to refuſe, and ſo to become moſt odious in the ſight of all the French na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yea, ſome gaue him warning that ſhe laboured the townes round about to put in practiſe the execution of the laſt Edict, alſo that fayning to ſeeke the general be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of the whole eſtate, ſhee wrought perticulerly much miſchiefe againſt the Towne of <hi>Rochell.</hi> This perſwaſion bare ſome ſhewe of reaſon, eſpecially after that the Catholicks had ſurprized and ſeazed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Vouans</hi> and <hi>Fay-moniau:</hi> for notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they were things of ſmall or no importaunce, yet happening during the tyme of the treaty, it bred a further ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of other practizes: and withall the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> himſelf began to thinke that hee could not hope to obteyne any great matters at their hands, who tooke ſo much paynes to take ſuch ſmall trifles fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him: How beit the Queene ſo whotly followed this matter and lay ſo ſore vpon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26389:14"/> him, that finally he agreed to yeeld to a ſecond enteruiewe, eyther to the ende to giue to all men to vnderſtand that he was not in fault that they treated not vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meanes for peace, eyther els perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelfe that the Queene would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer take ſo much paynes to the end twiſe to impart vnto him one bad tale. Vppon her comming therefore to <hi>Fontenaye</hi> hee came to <hi>Marans:</hi> and as their deſires to ſee each other, encreaſed, ſo did miſtruſt alſo ſpring vp among their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailes. The Queene, or rather ſome of hers, doubted to come to any place where the <hi>Rochellers</hi> were the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, and by reaſon there was a ſpeech giuen out that the Coronell En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of <hi>Rochell</hi> kept the paſſage of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uire</hi> they made a difficultie to come ouer: The King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> feared the crookes and bywayes of theſe Fennes, and in deed the nature of the place is ſuch, that euen one man alone may woorke a great feate there without any daunger. In the meane tyme the Queene was warned that the League grewe into miſtruſt of her acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: alſo that ſhee encroched too much
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:26389:15"/> vppon the Kings authoritie, and that her preſence were requiſite at <hi>Paris.</hi> Vppon this ſhe ſent to the King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him to ſend vnto her the Vicount of <hi>Touraine,</hi> with whom ſhe offered to ſpeak in all libertie, whereto he eaſely conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. This was the very knot of all the laſt treaty. The Queene gaue out that beeing enformed of his diſcretion and wiſedome ſhee would treate with him: The King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> being aſſured of his fidelitie did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent thereto: euery man generally, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing him to bee a louer of his Countrey, and ſuch a one as ſought the wealth and peace of this Eſtate, did wiſh for him. And my ſelfe was certefied by ſuch others as did more perticulerly knowe him, that he was a moſt fit inſtrument, in caſe at the handes of the Queenes Councell he had bene ſo entreated as he ought. Well, he came to <hi>Fontenaye,</hi> where hee gaue the Queene to vnderſtande of his comming, and that he there ſtayed to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: She propounded vnto him that it was expedient to agree vpon a generall truce, for that the affaires
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26389:15"/> were ſuche, as it was no tyme as yet to ſpeake of a finall peace: hereto he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> would ſone condiſcend to the ſame, and could be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſtill to alowe of the name of a truce, in caſe it might bring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruites of a peace: but that as yet they had ſo ſtopped their eares againſt his requeſts, that, to the end to procure audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, he was forced to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploye his friendes, without whoſe aduice and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent it now lay not in him to treate or conclude vpon eyther peace or a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall truce: That he was choſen protector of the one part, which the King had forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, conſiſting of ſondrie particuler per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who all had perticulerly bene iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed, and therefore could not bee ſatiſfied vnleſſe their complaints might be heard: That if it might pleaſe her Maieſtie to graunt ſuch Paſſeports as were requiſite, with tyme conuenient to call them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they would vſe al diligence: Further, that for the ſpeedyer proſecuting of this matter, it were not amiſſe, in his opinion, to conclude vpon a perticuler truce tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout that Prouince for two moneths,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26389:16"/> during the which the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> might come to ſee her, &amp; with her to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult vpon ſome meanes for peace, for the concluding whereof the Deputies of the Prouinces might make their repayre the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: This truce the Queene miſliking, ſhe commanded her Councell to declare her reaſons: whervpon one of them ſhewed it to bee preiuditiall to the King: for that, ſayd he, during the ſame, the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre</hi> might haue fit oportunitie to bring in ſtrangers: The Catholicks waxing ydle ſhould giue themſelues to reſt: Thoſe of the League would take this truce to be a ſhadowe of peace, for feare of the bodie whereof they might raiſe a ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To all this the Vicount anſwered, that the place wherby the ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers might enter had no correſpondence with either the high or low <hi>Poictow:</hi> alſo that the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of either peace or truce did rather hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aduance the leauie of them: That the ſecond reaſon was common to both parts, &amp; that thoſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did more abuſe their reſt then the Catholickes, as hauing bene leſſe accuſtomed thereunto:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:26389:16"/> As for the riſings of the League he knewe no remedie for them, as not hauing as yet taſted the inconueniences of the ſame: That the Duke of <hi>Guyze</hi> was but meanely accompanyed: That the Duke of <hi>Mayne</hi> had vndone his owne bande, and that of ſmall ruynes men neuer vſed to raiſe any great buyldings. But becauſe hetherto the ſayd Vicount had ſpoken without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, as one that came onely to heare, the Queene was of opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he ſhould returne to the King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> to the end by himſelfe to bee more perticulerly enſtructed of his mynd, which he did: and finding the king fully certefied of the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie of his Reyſters, by a meſſenger that came to him the ſame day, he ſpeedily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Queene, whom he found at <hi>Nyort</hi> reſolued vppon her returne to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi> There had he audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and did at large before her Maieſtie diſcourſe vppon the happie eſtate of the King of <hi>Nauarres</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres: viz. That he had borne the burden of fiue Armies, which had ſerued to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purpoſe but to ſhewe what he was in reſpect of his enemies power: That con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywiſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:26389:17"/> they were waſted as well in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer as credite: That they had recourſe to the conſpiraties and ſeditions of a towne, as not able to proſecute the warres in the field: That they were to expect no further ſuccour from the <hi>Spanyard,</hi> who now was ſo buſied in his own defence, that he had not ſo much leaſure as to dreame of ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them with meanes to aſſayle: That notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> hath loſt ſome few ſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces or rather Douecotes, yet hath he fortefied fiftie Houlds, &amp; that albeit hetherto he ſtood vppon his owne defence, yet was it at his diſcretion to make his enemies take his part: That he hath in readineſſe a great and ſtrong for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayne ayde which no neceſsitie of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres did euer force him to call in, which alſo he was not purpoſed to haue vſed for warre, but to the end to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter peace: That although he had bene di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly and highly iniuryed, yet it neuer ſancke into his mind to ſeeke any reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge againſt thoſe whom he knewe to bee ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to this Crowne. The Lord of <hi>Neuers</hi> aſked him whether hee had not bounde
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:26389:17"/> himſelfe to any to the preiudice of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate: But hee, proſecuting his diſcourſe, moſt humbly beſought the Queene to iudge of himſelf that he was neither raſh, neither a lyer, alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would not once ſet forth a foote to report any thing that he were not well aſſured of, &amp; that knowing the trueth, he would not cloke it: which was, That the King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> had made no other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract with ſtrangers then ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the wealth and peace of the eſtate, and to the reſtoring of the King and his faithfull ſeruants vnto their due authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And to the end Madame, ſayd he, that you may the better iudge of his entent, I doe here proteſt vnto you that whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it may pleaſe your Maieſties to vſe his power and forces, he will euermore moſt readily turne his face to what part ſoeuer that the benefite of this Realme, together with your commandements ſhal cal him. The King of <hi>Nauarre</hi> hath alwaies bene of that opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that in aſmuch as the king entred into this warre becauſe he was the weaker, it was not poſsible for him to make any peace vnleſſe he could grow the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:26389:18"/> ſtronger, which in trueth he ſhal do when the Princes of his blood ſhal haue in their hands ſufficient power wherwith to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the yeelding of that obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which vnto him is due. This Madame is the laſt remedie, and I would to God wee could eſchue it, and perticulerly I doe declare it vnto you as your Maieſties ſeruant, not as a profeſſor of the Religion: That perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture it wil be more ſafetie for vs to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend an Armie then a Parley, and a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile then an edict. Thinke not Madame, that the eſtate ſhall feele the diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of her friendes. It is vnto you both profite and honor willingly to conſent to a peace, and in tyme rather in your owne good affection to chooſe the meanes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when neceſsitie ſhall compell you, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept at al aduentures of ſuch as force ſhal preſcribe. Then the Queene ſayde that it were meet to ſtay the forraine power, and a while ſtood vpon the forme of the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, wherevppon the Vicount ſayd: If Madame you doe ſtand in doubt to giue vs good words, we are not belike yet nere the poynt to looke for any good effects,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:26389:18"/> which we ſhould lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger delay if we ſhould ſtay that power that may moue you ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. It is no tyme for vs Madame, any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to aſſure our ſelues vpon a bare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, ſith euen the moſt ſolemne edicts do fayle vs.</p>
            <p>The Queene gaue ſo good eare to theſe reaſons, that her heart ſeemed to bee by them the more bent to conſider of ſuch aduertiſements as were daylie on euery ſide brought vnto her. Thei ſet before her the apparance of a mightie ſedition: The King but badly accompanyed: The Duke of <hi>Mayne</hi> in <hi>Paris:</hi> The Duke of <hi>Guyze</hi> alſo readie to enter in. They ſhewed her what occaſions the Capteynes of the League now had to ſhoote of the laſt ſhot of their diſpayre, as that their hope to enioye <hi>England</hi> was now dead with the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Queene: That our Cleargymens deuotion deminiſhed as faſt as their am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition encreaſed: That fower Armies had bene ſpoyled for default of meanes: That thoſe of the Religion waxed ſtronger and ſtronger, and therefore that there was no further apparance that theſe our maiſters
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:26389:19"/> can buyld any more vppon their ruynes. All theſe things which wee moſt feared ſo ſuncke into her imagination that ſhee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth in haſte, to ſtoppe, as it is likely, theſe ſedicious perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, who haue no more left to enterpriſe or execute but finally vpon the Kings perſon. Thus may you ſee the effect of our treatie, and ſo the end of my letter which would haue wearyed me to write, had I not forgot the labour of my hande through that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which I conceiue in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terteyning of you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I doe moſt humbly kiſse your hands, and remaine your moſt faithfull ſeruant. S. C. P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26389:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26389:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
